Have you ever wondered what animals think and feel?
هل تساءلت يومًا عمّا يفكر فيه الحيوانات أو يشعرون به؟
Let's start with a question:
فلنبدأ بسؤال:
Does my dog really love me, or does she just want a treat?
هل تُحبّني كلبتي، أم هي فقط تُحبّ اعتنائي بها؟
Well, it's easy to see that our dog really loves us,
حسنًا، من الواضح أن كلبتنا تحبنا حقًا،
easy to see, right,
من السهل رؤية ذلك، صحيح،
what's going on in that fuzzy little head.
ما الذي يجول في ذلك الرأس الصغير الغامض؟
What is going on?
ما الذي يجري؟
Something's going on.
هناك شيء ما يجري.
But why is the question always do they love us?
ولكن لماذا يكون السؤال دائمًا هل يحبوننا؟
Why is it always about us?
لماذا دائمًا يتعلق الأمر بنا؟
Why are we such narcissists?
لماذا نحن نرجسيون؟
I found a different question to ask animals.
لقد وجدت سؤالًا مختلفًا لطرحه على الحيوانات.
Who are you?
من أنتم؟
There are capacities of the human mind
هناك قدرات للعقل البشري
that we tend to think are capacities only of the human mind.
نعتقد أنها خاصة بالعقل البشري فقط.
But is that true?
ولكن هل هذا صحيح؟
What are other beings doing with those brains?
ما الذي تقوم به الكائنات البشرية الأخرى بتلك الأدمغة؟
What are they thinking and feeling?
ما الذي يفكرون فيه وما الذي يشعرون به؟
Is there a way to know?
هل هناك طريقة لمعرفة ذلك؟
I think there is a way in.
أعتقد بأنه توجد طريقة.
I think there are several ways in.
أعتقد بأنه توجد عدة طرق.
We can look at evolution, we can look at their brains
بإمكاننا النظر في التطور، بإمكاننا النظر لأدمغتهم
and we can watch what they do.
وبإمكاننا مراقبة ما يقومون به.
The first thing to remember is: our brain is inherited.
أول شيء يجب تذكره هو بأننا ورثنا أدمغتنا.
The first neurons came from jellyfish.
الخلايا العصبية الأولى كانت من قنديل البحر.
Jellyfish gave rise to the first chordates.
كانت قناديل البحر أساس الحبليات الأولى.
The first chordates gave rise to the first vertebrates.
والحبليات الأولى هي أساس الفقاريات الأولى.
The vertebrates came out of the sea,
خرجت الفقاريات من البحر،
and here we are.
وها نحن هنا.
But it's still true that a neuron, a nerve cell, looks the same
ولكن تبقى الحقيقة بأن خلية عصبية هي نفسها
in a crayfish, a bird or you.
عند جراد البحر أو العصفور أو أنت.
What does that say about the minds of crayfish?
ما الذي يخبرنا هذا عن عقل جراد البحر؟
Can we tell anything about that?
هل يمكن أن نعرف أي شيء عن هذا؟
Well, it turns out that if you give a crayfish
حسنًا، لقد اتضح أنه عند صعق جراد البحر
a lot of little tiny electric shocks
بالكثير من الصدمات الكهربائية الصغيرة
every time it tries to come out of its burrow,
في كل مرة تحاول فيها الخروج من جحرها،
it will develop anxiety.
يُسبّب لها ذلك نوعًا من التوتر.
If you give the crayfish the same drug
وإن ناولت جراد البحر نفس الدواء الذي
used to treat anxiety disorder in humans,
تستعمله الكائنات البشرية لمعالجة هذا الاضطراب،
it relaxes and comes out and explores.
فيسترخي ويخرج من جحره ويكتشف.
How do we show how much we care about crayfish anxiety?
كيف نعبّر عن اهتمامنا بتوتّر جراد البحر؟
Mostly, we boil them.
في الغالب، نقوم بسلقهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Octopuses use tools, as well as do most apes
تستعمل الأخطبوطات وسائلًا كما هو الحال بالنسبة للقردة
and they recognize human faces.
ويتعرفون على الوجوه البشرية.
How do we celebrate the ape-like intelligence of this invertebrate?
كيف نحتفل بذكاء مثل ذكاء القردة لهذه اللافقاريات؟
Mostly boiled.
غالبًا، مسلوقة.
If a grouper chases a fish into a crevice in the coral,
إذا طارد القُشر سمكة بثغرة في المرجان،
it will sometimes go to where it knows a moray eel is sleeping
سوف يذهب في الغالب إلى مكان تنام به المورايية
and it will signal to the moray, "Follow me,"
وسيعطيه إشارة ليتبعه،
and the moray will understand that signal.
وستفهم المورايية تلك الإشارة.
The moray may go into the crevice and get the fish,
ربما ستدخل المورايية في الثغر لتفتك بالسمكة،
but the fish may bolt and the grouper may get it.
ولكن يمكن أن تهرب السمكة ويمكن أن تحصل عليها القُشر.
This is an ancient partnership that we have just recently found out about.
هذه شراكة قديمة اكتشفناها مُؤخّرًا.
How do we celebrate that ancient partnership?
كيف نحتفل بتلك الشراكة القديمة؟
Mostly fried.
غالبًا مقلية.
A pattern is emerging and it says a lot more about us
وثمة نموذج بدأ في الظهور ويقول الكثير بشأننا
than it does about them.
أكثر مما يقول بشأنهم.
Sea otters use tools
تستعمل القُضاعات البحرية وسائلًا
and they take time away from what they're doing
ويأخذون استراحة مما يقومون به
to show their babies what to do, which is called teaching.
لتُظهر لأطفالها ما الذي يجب القيام به وهو ما يُسمّى التعليم.
Chimpanzees don't teach.
الشمبانزي لا تُعلّم.
Killer whales teach and killer whales share food.
الحيتان القاتلة تُعلّم وتتقاسم الطعام.
When evolution makes something new,
عندما يُحدث التطوّر شيئًا جديدًا،
it uses the parts it has in stock, off the shelf,
فهو يرتكز على الأجزاء المُخزّنة، المُتوفّرة،
before it fabricates a new twist.
قبل أن تأخذ منعطفًا جديدًا.
And our brain has come to us
وأدمغتنا هي نتيجة
through the enormity of the deep sweep of time.
الاجتياح الضخم للزمن.
If you look at the human brain compared to a chimpanzee brain,
إذا تأملت العقل البشري مقارنة بعقل الشمبانزي،
what you see is we have basically a very big chimpanzee brain.
ما ستلاحظه هو امتلاكنا لعقل الشمبانزي ولكن بحجم كبير.
It's a good thing ours is bigger, because we're also really insecure.
هذا جيد أن عقلنا أكبر، لأننا أيضًا حقًا غير آمنين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But, uh oh, there's a dolphin,
ولكن، أوه، أوه، هناك دلفين،
a bigger brain with more convolutions.
عقل أكبر مع تلافيف أكثر.
OK, maybe you're saying, all right, well, we see brains,
حسنًا، ربما ستقولون، حسنًا، نحن نرى أدمغة،
but what does that have to say about minds?
ولكن ماهي صلة ذلك بالعقل؟
Well, we can see the working of the mind
حسنًا، يمكن أن نرى طريقة عمل العقل
in the logic of behaviors.
في منطق التصرّفات.
So these elephants, you can see,
إذن هذه الفيلة كما ترون،
obviously, they are resting.
من الواضح أنهم يأخذون قسطًا من الراحة.
They have found a patch of shade under the palm trees
لقد وجدوا مكانًا به ظل تحت النخيل
under which to let their babies sleep,
حيث يمكن لأطفالهم النوم،
while they doze but remain vigilant.
بينما يغفون ولكن يظلون يقظين.
We make perfect sense of that image
نحن نقوم بوصف منطقي للصورة
just as they make perfect sense of what they're doing
تمامًا مثل ما يقومون به
because under the arc of the same sun on the same plains,
لأنه تحت أشعة نفس الشمس، على نفس السهول،
listening to the howls of the same dangers,
يستمعون إلى العويل لنفس الخطر؟
they became who they are and we became who we are.
هم أصبحوا على ما هم عليه ونحن أصبحنا ما نحن عليه.
We've been neighbors for a very long time.
لقد كنا جيرانًا لمدة طويلة.
No one would mistake these elephants as being relaxed.
لن يفهم أحد على وجه الخطأ بأن هؤلاء الفيلة في وضع استرخاء.
They're obviously very concerned about something.
من الواضح أنهم قلقون بخصوص شيء ما.
What are they concerned about?
ما الذي يشعرون بالقلق إزائه؟
It turns out that if you record the voices of tourists
اتضح أنه إذا سجلت أصوات السياح
and you play that recording from a speaker hidden in bushes,
وعرضت هذا التسجيل بواسطة مكبر صوت مخبأ بالأدغال،
elephants will ignore it, because tourists never bother elephants.
سوف يتجاهل الفيلة ذلك الصوت، لأن السياح لا يُزعجون الفيلة.
But if you record the voices of herders
ولكن إن قمت بتسجيل أصوات الرعاة
who carry spears and often hurt elephants in confrontations at water holes,
الحاملين للرماح ودائمًا ما يُؤذون الفيلة في مواجهات في المياه،
the elephants will bunch up and run away from the hidden speaker.
سوف تتجمع الفيلة وتهرب من مكبر الصوت المُخبأ.
Not only do elephants know that there are humans,
الفيلة لا تعرف فقط بأنه توجد كائنات بشرية،
they know that there are different kinds of humans,
ولكنها تعرف بوجود أنواع من الكائنات البشرية،
and that some are OK and some are dangerous.
وبأن هناك من لا يلحقون بهم الأذية ومن هم خطرون.
They have been watching us for much longer than we have been watching them.
لقد كانوا يراقبوننا أكثر مما نراقبهم.
They know us better than we know them.
هم يعرفوننا أكثر مما نعرفهم.
We have the same imperatives:
لدينا نفس الأولويات:
take care of our babies, find food, try to stay alive.
نرعى أطفالنا، نُوفّر الطعام ونُحاول البقاء على قيد الحياة.
Whether we're outfitted for hiking in the hills of Africa
سواء كنا جاهزين للمشي على تلال أفريقيا
or outfitted for diving under the sea, we are basically the same.
أم جاهزين للغوص تحت الماء، نحن نعتمد نفس الأساس.
We are kin under the skin.
نحن أقرباء.
The elephant has the same skeleton,
تملك الفيلة نفس الهيكل العظمي،
the killer whale has the same skeleton,
تملك الحيتان القاتلة نفس الهيكل العظمي،
as do we.
مثلنا.
We see helping where help is needed.
نرى المساعدة عندما يكون هناك حاجة للمساعدة.
We see curiosity in the young.
نرى الفضول في الشباب.
We see the bonds of family connections.
نرى روابطًا للعلاقات العائلية.
We recognize affection.
نلاحظ العاطفة والانسجام.
Courtship is courtship.
المغازلة هي المغازلة.
And then we ask, "Are they conscious?"
وثم نسأل، "هل هم واعون؟"
When you get general anesthesia, it makes you unconscious,
عندما يتم تخديرك بالكامل هذا يجعلك غير واعٍ،
which means you have no sensation of anything.
مما يعني أنك لا تشعر بأي شيء.
Consciousness is simply the thing that feels like something.
الوعي بكل بساطة هو إحساسك بالشيء.
If you see, if you hear, if you feel, if you're aware of anything,
ما إن كنت تسمع، تشعر، أو على علم بأي شيء.
you are conscious, and they are conscious.
أنت واعِ وهم واعون.
Some people say
بعض الناس يقولون
well, there are certain things that make humans humans,
حسنا، هناك أشياء تجعل من البشر بشرًا،
and one of those things is empathy.
وأحد هذه الأشياء هي التعاطف.
Empathy is the mind's ability to match moods with your companions.
التعاطف هو قدرة العقل على انسجام الحالات المزاجية مع أصدقائك.
It's a very useful thing.
هي شيء مفيد جدًّا.
If your companions start to move quickly,
إذا بدأ أصدقاؤك في التحرك بسرعة،
you have to feel like you need to hurry up.
يجب عليك الشعور بأنه يجب الإسراع.
We're all in a hurry now.
نحن جميعنا مستعجلون الآن.
The oldest form of empathy is contagious fear.
الشكل القديم للتعاطف هو الخوف المعدي.
If your companions suddenly startle and fly away,
في صورة فزع أصدقائك فجأة وهروبهم،
it does not work very well for you to say,
ليس من المنطق أن تقول،
"Jeez, I wonder why everybody just left."
"آه، لماذا غادر الجميع؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Empathy is old, but empathy, like everything else in life,
التعاطف هو شيء قديم، ولكن التعاطف، مثل أي شيء في الحياة،
comes on a sliding scale and has its elaboration.
يأتي على مقياس معين، ولديه تفاصيله.
So there's basic empathy: you feel sad, it makes me sad.
إذن هذا أساس التعاطف: أنت تشعر بالحزن، هذا يجعلني حزينًا.
I see you happy, it makes me happy.
أراك سعيدًا، هذا يُسعدني.
Then there's something that I call sympathy,
ثم هناك شيء أسميه الشفقة،
a little more removed:
وهو أبعد بقليل:
"I'm sorry to hear that your grandmother has just passed away.
"أنا آسف لسماع خبر وفاة جدتك.
I don't feel that same grief, but I get it; I know what you feel
أنا لا أشعر بالحزن نفسه، ولكن أعرف ذلك، أنا أعرف ما تشعر به
and it concerns me."
وهذا يهمني."
And then if we're motivated to act on sympathy,
وإذا تم تحفيزنا للتظاهر بالشفقة،
I call that compassion.
أسمي ذلك الإحساس بالشفقة.
Far from being the thing that makes us human,
بعيدًا عن الشيء الذي يجعل منا بشرًا،
human empathy is far from perfect.
التعاطف الإنساني هو أبعد ما يكون عن الكمال.
We round up empathic creatures, we kill them and we eat them.
نجمع المخلوقات المسكينة، نقتلها ونأكلها.
Now, maybe you say OK, well, those are different species.
حاليًا، ربما تقولون نعم، حسنا، تلك أنواع مختلفة.
That's just predation, and humans are predators.
هذا افتراس، والبشر مفترسون.
But we don't treat our own kind too well either.
ولكننا لا نُعامل بعضنا البعض جيدًا أيضًا.
People who seem to know only one thing about animal behavior
الأشخاص الذين يبدو أنهم يعرفون شيئًا واحدًا حول سلوك الحيوان
know that you must never attribute human thoughts and emotions
يعرفون جيدًا أنه لا يجب أن تُنسب أفكار البشر وعواطفهم
to other species.
إلى أصناف أخرى.
Well, I think that's silly,
حسنًا، أعتقد أن هذا تافه.
because attributing human thoughts and emotions to other species
لأنك عندما تنسب أفكار البشر وعواطفهم إلى أصناف أخرى
is the best first guess about what they're doing and how they're feeling,
فهذه أفضل أول تخمين لما يقومون به وكيف يشعرون،
because their brains are basically the same as ours.
لأن أدمغتهم في الأساس هي مثل أدمغتنا.
They have the same structures.
لديهم نفس الهيكل.
The same hormones that create mood and motivation in us
نفس الهرمونات التي تساهم في التحكم في مزاجنا وتحفيزنا
are in those brains as well.
هي في أدمغتهم أيضًا.
It is not scientific to say that they are hungry when they're hunting
ليس علميًا أن نجزم بأنهم جائعون عندما يصطادون
and they're tired when their tongues are hanging out,
وأنهم متعبون عندما تكون ألسنتهم خارج أفواههم،
and then say when they're playing with their children
وأنهم عندما يلعبون مع أطفالهم
and acting joyful and happy,
ويدعون الفرح والسعادة،
we have no idea if they can possibly be experiencing anything.
ليس لدينا أدنى فكرة عما إذا كانوا يختبرون أي شيء.
That is not scientific.
هذا ليس علميًا.
So OK, so a reporter said to me,
حسنا، إذن قال لي مراسل،
"Maybe, but how do you really know that other animals can think and feel?"
"ربما، ولكن كيف تعرف حقًا أن الحيوانات الأخرى يمكنها أن تُفكّر وتشعر؟"
And I started to rifle through all the hundreds
وبدأت في البحث في آلاف
of scientific references that I put in my book
المراجع العلمية التي وضعتها بكتابي
and I realized that the answer was right in the room with me.
وأدركت أن الإجابة كانت ماثلة أمامي.
When my dog gets off the rug and comes over to me --
عندما تنتقل كلبتي من على البساط وتتوجّه نحوي --
not to the couch, to me --
ليس نحو الأريكة ولكن نحوي --
and she rolls over on her back and exposes her belly,
وتستلقي على ظهرها وتكشف عن بطنها،
she has had the thought, "I would like my belly rubbed.
ولديها فكرة، "أريد أن يفرك بطني.
I know that I can go over to Carl,
أعلم أنه يمكنني أن أذهب إلى كارل،
he will understand what I'm asking.
سوف يفهم ما أطلبه.
I know I can trust him because we're family.
أعلم أنه بإمكاني أن أثق به لأننا عائلة.
He'll get the job done, and it will feel good."
سوف يقوم بالمهمة وسيشعرني ذلك بالراحة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
She has thought and she has felt,
لقد فكرت وشعرت،
and it's really not more complicated than that.
وفي الحقيقة ذلك ليس معقدًا لتلك الدرجة.
But we see other animals and we say, "Oh look, killer whales,
ولكننا ننظر إلى الحيوانات الأخرى ونقول، "أوه، اُنظر حيتان قاتلة،
wolves, elephants:
ذئاب، فيلة:
that's not how they see it."
هم لا يرون ذلك بهذا الشكل."
That tall-finned male is L41.
ذلك الذكر طويل القامة ذو الزعانف هو L41.
He's 38 years old.
يبلغ من العمر 38 سنة.
The female right on his left side is L22.
والأنثى التي بجانبه على اليسار هي L22.
She's 44.
تبلغ من العمر 44 سنة.
They've known each other for decades.
وهما يعرفان بعضهما البعض منذ عقود.
They know exactly who they are.
هما يعرفان بالضبط أنفسهما.
They know who their friends are.
يعرفان أصدقائهما.
They know who their rivals are.
يعرفان منافسيهما.
Their life follows the arc of a career.
حياتهما تتبع مهنتهما.
They know where they are all the time.
هما يعرفان مكانهما دائمًا.
This is an elephant named Philo.
هذا فيل اسمه فيلو.
He was a young male.
كان شابًا.
This is him four days later.
هذا هو بعد أربعة أيام.
Humans not only can feel grief, we create an awful lot of it.
البشر لا يشعرون فقط بالحزن، بل نخلق الكثير منه.
We want to carve their teeth.
نحن نريد أن ننحت أسنانهم.
Why can't we wait for them to die?
لماذا لا ننتظر موتهم؟
Elephants once ranged from the shores of the Mediterranean Sea
انتشرت الفيلة من شواطئ البحر الأبيض المتوسط
all the way down to the Cape of Good Hope.
وصولًا إلى معبر"رأس الرجاء الصالح".
In 1980, there were vast strongholds of elephant range
في سنة 1980، كانت هناك معاقل واسعة لمجموعات من الفيلة
in Central and Eastern Africa.
في وسط وشرق أفريقيا.
And now their range is shattered into little shards.
والآن تحطمت تلك المجموعة إلى شظايا صغيرة.
This is the geography of an animal that we are driving to extinction,
هذه جغرافيا حيوان سنتسبب في انقراضه،
a fellow being, the most magnificent creature on land.
مخلوق صديق، أروع مخلوق على الأرض.
Of course, we take much better care of our wildlife in the United States.
بالطبع، نحن نعطي رعاية أكبر للحياة البرية في الولايات المتحدة.
In Yellowstone National Park, we killed every single wolf.
في حديقة يلوستون الوطنية، قتلنا كل ذئب أعزب.
We killed every single wolf south of the Canadian border, actually.
قتلنا كل ذئب أعزب جنوب الحدود الكندية، في الواقع.
But in the park, park rangers did that in the 1920s,
ولكن في الحديقة، قام حراس الحديقة بذلك سنة 1920،
and then 60 years later they had to bring them back,
وبعد 60 سنة توجّب عليهم إعادة جلبهم،
because the elk numbers had gotten out of control.
لأن عدد الأيائل قد خرج عن السيطرة.
And then people came.
ثم جاء الأشخاص.
People came by the thousands to see the wolves,
أتى الناس بالآلاف لرؤية الذئاب،
the most accessibly visible wolves in the world.
الذئاب المتاحة أكثر في العالم ويمكن رؤيتها.
And I went there and I watched this incredible family of wolves.
وذهبت هناك وشاهدت هذه العائلة المدهشة من الذئاب.
A pack is a family.
القطيع يُمثّل عائلة.
It has some breeding adults and the young of several generations.
تحتوي على الكهول التي تربي وعدد من الصغار من أجيال مختلفة.
And I watched the most famous, most stable pack in Yellowstone National Park.
وشاهدت القطيع الأكثر شهرة واستقرارًا بحديقة يلوستون الوطنية.
And then, when they wandered just outside the border,
وعند تجولهم خارج الحدود،
two of their adults were killed,
قٌتل كهلين منهم،
including the mother,
بما في ذلك الأم،
which we sometimes call the alpha female.
والتي ندعوها في بعض الأحيان "الأنثى المتسلطة"
The rest of the family immediately descended into sibling rivalry.
اتجه بقية أفراد العائلة إلى التنافس الأخوي.
Sisters kicked out other sisters.
قام الأخوات بطرد الأخوات الأخريات.
That one on the left tried for days to rejoin her family.
وحاولت الأخرى على اليسار الالتحاق بعائلتها على مدار أيام.
They wouldn't let her because they were jealous of her.
ولم يسمحوا لها بذلك لأنهم كانوا يشعرون بالغيرة تُجاهها.
She was getting too much attention from two new males,
لقد كانت تحظى باهتمام كبير من قبل ذكرين جديدين،
and she was the precocious one.
ولقد كانت مبكّرة النضوج.
That was too much for them.
حيث كان ذلك كثيرًا بالنسبة لهم.
She wound up wandering outside the park and getting shot.
وانتهى بها الأمر بالتجول خارج الحديقة والتعرض لإطلاق نار.
The alpha male wound up being ejected from his own family.
انتهى الأمر "بالذكر المتسلّط" بطرده من قبل عائلته.
As winter was coming in,
وبدخول فصل الشتاء،
he lost his territory, his hunting support,
فقد أرضه وركيزة صيده،
the members of his family and his mate.
وأفراد عائلته ورفيقه.
We cause so much pain to them.
نحن نتسبب لهم بالكثير من الألم.
The mystery is, why don't they hurt us more than they do?
واللغز هو لما لا يقومون بأذيتنا أكثر مما يقومون به؟
This whale had just finished eating part of a grey whale
هذا الحوت القاتل انتهى لتوّه من أكل جزء من الحوت الرمادي
with his companions who had killed that whale.
مع أصدقائه الذين قاموا بقتله.
Those people in the boat had nothing at all to fear.
هؤلاء الأشخاص على القارب لم يكن لديهم أي داع للخوف على الإطلاق.
This whale is T20.
هذا الحوت هو T20.
He had just finished tearing a seal into three pieces with two companions.
انتهى لتوه من تمزيق فقمة إلى 3 أجزاء مع صديقين.
The seal weighed about as much as the people in the boat.
كان وزن الفقمة يُعادل تقريبًا وزن الأشخاص بالقارب.
They had nothing to fear.
لا يوجد داع للخوف.
They eat seals.
فهم يأكلون الفقمات.
Why don't they eat us?
لماذا لا يأكلوننا نحن؟
Why can we trust them around our toddlers?
لماذا نستطيع أن نأتمنهم حول أطفالنا؟
Why is it that killer whales have returned to researchers lost in thick fog
لماذا رجع هذا الحوت القاتل لباحثين ضائعين في الضباب
and led them miles until the fog parted
وقادهم أميالًا إلى أن اختفى الضباب
and the researchers' home was right there on the shoreline?
وكان منزلهم على حافة الشاطئ؟
And that's happened more than one time.
وحصل هذا أكثر من مرة واحدة.
In the Bahamas, there's a woman named Denise Herzing,
في جزر البهاما، هناك امرأة تُدعى دينيس هرزنغ.
and she studies spotted dolphins and they know her.
وتدرس عن الدلفين المبقع ويعرفونها.
She knows them very well. She knows who they all are.
هي تعرفهم جيدًا. هي تعرفهم من هم.
They know her. They recognize the research boat.
هم يعرفونها. يعرفون قارب البحوث الخاص بها.
When she shows up, it's a big happy reunion.
عندما تظهر. فإنه اجتماع كبير تنبثق منه السعادة.
Except, one time showed up and they didn't want to come near the boat,
ما عدا مرّة واحدة عندما ظهرت ولكن لم يقتربوا من القارب،
and that was really strange.
وكان هذا فعلًا غريبًا.
And they couldn't figure out what was going on
ولم يكونوا قادرين على معرفة ما الذي يجري
until somebody came out on deck
حتى ظهر شخص من على ظهر السفينة
and announced that one of the people onboard had died
وأعلن عن وفاة أحد الأشخاص الذي كان على متن السفينة
during a nap in his bunk.
بينما كان يأخذ قيلولة في سريره.
How could dolphins know that one of the human hearts
كيف يمكن أن تعرف الدلافين أن قلب الإنسان
had just stopped?
قد توقف؟
Why would they care?
لماذا قد يهتمون بذلك؟
And why would it spook them?
ولماذا يُخيفهم ذلك؟
These mysterious things just hint at all of the things that are going on
هذه الأشياء الغامضة التي تشير إلى الأشياء التي تجري الآن
in the minds that are with us on Earth
في عقول كائنات تعيش معنا على الأرض
that we almost never think about at all.
والتي تقريبًا لم نفكر فيها مطلقًا.
At an aquarium in South Africa
في حوض للأسماك بجنوب أفريقيا
was a little baby bottle-nosed dolphin named Dolly.
كان هناك دلفين صغير اسمه دولي.
She was nursing, and one day a keeper took a cigarette break
كات ترضع، وفي يوم ما أخذ الحارس استراحة لتدخين سيجارة
and he was looking into the window into their pool, smoking.
وكان ينظر إلى الحوض ويُدخّن.
Dolly came over and looked at him,
اقترب دولي ونظر إليه،
went back to her mother, nursed for a minute or two,
رجع إلى أمه ورضع قرابة دقيقة أو دقيقتين،
came back to the window
رجع إلى الشباك،
and released a cloud of milk that enveloped her head like smoke.
ورسم سحابة من الحليب حول رأسه مثل الدخان.
Somehow, this baby bottle-nosed dolphin
بطريقة ما، خطرت للدلفين
got the idea of using milk to represent smoke.
طريقة استعمال الحليب لتمثيل الدخان.
When human beings use one thing to represent another,
عندما يستعمل الإنسان شيئا ما لتمثيل شيء آخر،
we call that art.
يُسمّى ذلك فنّا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The things that make us human
الشيء الذي يجعل منا إنسانيين
are not the things that we think make us human.
ليست الأشياء التي نعتقد أنها تجعل منا إنسانيين.
What makes us human is that,
ما يجعلنا إنسانيين هو،
of all these things that our minds and their minds have,
كل تلك الأشياء التي لدينا بعقولنا ولديهم بعقولهم،
we are the most extreme.
نحن الأكثر تطرفًا.
We are the most compassionate,
نحن الأكثر رحمة،
most violent, most creative
الأكثر عنفًا والأكثر إبداعًا
and most destructive animal that has ever been on this planet,
والحيوان الأكثر تسببًا في التدمير على هذه الأرض،
and we are all of those things all jumbled up together.
ونحن مزيج من كل تلك الأشياء،
But love is not the thing that makes us human.
ولكن الحب ليس ما يجعل منا إنسانيين.
It's not special to us.
هو ليس شيئًا استثنائيًا بالنسبة لنا.
We are not the only ones who care about our mates.
لسنا الوحيدين المهتمين بشركائنا.
who care about our children.
لسنا الوحيدين المهتمين بأطفالنا.
Albatrosses frequently fly six, sometimes ten thousand miles
يطير القطرس 6 ألاف وأحيانًا عشرة آلاف ميل
over several weeks to deliver one meal, one big meal,
مدة عدة أسابيع للحصول على وجبة واحدة، وجبة واحدة كبيرة،
to their chick who is waiting for them.
لأطفالهم المنتظرين.
They nest on the most remote islands in the oceans of the world,
فهم يبنون أعشاشهم في أكثر البلدان النائية من العالم،
and this is what it looks like.
وهذا ما يبدو عليه الأمر.
Passing life from one generation to the next is the chain of being.
المحافظة على الحياة من جيل إلى آخر هي سلسلة الوجود.
If that stops, it all goes away.
إذا توقف هذا، فسيندثر كل شيء.
If anything is sacred, that is, and into that sacred relationship
إذا كان أي شيء مُقدّس، فهذا هو، وفيما يتعلق بتلك العلاقة المقدسة،
comes our plastic trash.
تأتي الفضلات البلاستيكية.
All of these birds have plastic in them now.
كل تلك الطيور تحتوي على البلاستيك بداخلها.
This is an albatross six months old, ready to fledge --
هذا طائر القرطس عمره 6 أشهر في طور إنبات الريش --
died, packed with red cigarette lighters.
تُوفّي ومليء بقداحات السجائر.
This is not the relationship we are supposed to have
هذه ليست العلاقة التي من المفروض أن تكون
with the rest of the world.
مع بقية العالم.
But we, who have named ourselves after our brains,
ولكن نحن، من ندعي بأننا نمتلك أدمغة،
never think about the consequences.
لا نُفكّر في النتائج.
When we welcome new human life into the world,
عندما نُرحّب بإنسان جديد إلى العالم،
we welcome our babies into the company of other creatures.
نُرحّب بأطفالنا صحبة مخلوقات أُخرى.
We paint animals on the walls.
نرسم حيوانات على الحيطان.
We don't paint cell phones.
لا نرسم هواتف محمولة.
We don't paint work cubicles.
لا نرسم مقصورات عمل.
We paint animals to show them that we are not alone.
نرسم حيوانات لنُبين لهم بأننا لسنا لوحدنا.
We have company.
لدينا مُرافقون.
And every one of those animals in every painting of Noah's ark,
وكل حيوان من تلك الحيوانات في كل لوحة من سفينة نوح،
deemed worthy of salvation is in mortal danger now,
يعتقد أنه يستحق الإنقاذ هو في خطر مُحدق الآن،
and their flood is us.
وطوفانهم هو نحن.
So we started with a question:
إذن بدأنا بسؤال:
Do they love us?
هل يحبوننا؟
We're going to ask another question.
سنسأل سؤالًا آخر.
Are we capable of using what we have
هل نحن قادرون على استعمال ما لدينا
to care enough to simply let them continue?
للاهتمام كفاية بهم ونترك لهم المجال للمتابعة.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)